hello this is Frankie Freitas and
welcome to another week of Hall talk for
the week of March 26 2000 I'm in the
studio and Michelle Roy is with us again
this week hello Michelle how are you I'm
good Frank how are you I'm doing great
uh we're going to bring you the second
show in a series of five shows that we
recorded when we were out in Long Island
City New York at the center for the
holographic arts and today's guest is
Dan Schweitzer and Michelle you did the
interview with Dan and I just had a
chance to edit it and listen to its
great interview oh thanks I was just
sitting here trying to remember what we
talked about
I did I remember having a good time with
the interview
thanks for tuning in I guess we'll just
move right on to the show because I well
you can't think of anything else to say
I can't think of anything else to say
why don't you say something I think the
show pretty much speaks for itself it
was a good show we had fun lots of
laughing which is always great I think
in the show yeah
and uh that's it that is it all right
here's the show don't forget to tune in
each and every week and we'll have the
third show in the series next week so
thanks for tuning in to all talk see you
next week I thought you were doing Mary
no we're doing dance yeah
well the reason why we're doing Dan is
we did Anna Maria Nicholson last week
who was one of the directors and
Founders oh sure okay even though time
wise uh Mary was the second person we
interviewed I figured show wise it might
be good to do Dan because he's the
co-director coach yeah but that makes
sense you just didn't let me I wasn't in
on the thought process there oh I see
that was you know once you explain it to
me now it makes sense okay I'm with you
on that one already but you know so I'll
go over now and now you can turn this up
okay
please
we're back at the show
with Dan Schweitzer and Michelle Roy and
if you want to hear the interview that
we did previously with Dan just go right
onto the archive page and I think we
have a show there that lasts about 40 or
45 minutes with Dan so I'm not going to
repeat some of the questions that I
asked him during that show so what I'm
going to do is turn the microphone back
over to Michelle Roy who wants to ask
Dan a few questions about how to get
involved with photography and well
she'll be better to ask those questions
than I can to be able to tell you so
here she is especially the way you're
talking right now
I think Frank's been hitting the been
hitting the wine over
at any rate to return to the purpose of
being here Dan what I wanted to talk to
you first of all about was sort of your
own interest in work in holography in
terms of you know what got you
interested in doing this as a career
what you know made you decide you know
this as opposed to being a professor I
don't know anything yeah auto mechanics
exactly what got you into this
uh it's a serendipitous kind of
experience um I think I mentioned in a
prior interview with Frank that uh that
my my involvement was really by almost
by accident but once I I got my first
class in holography it was it was the
the concept beyond the recording process
was so extraordinary
and it just appealed to my philosophical
side as much as anything else and uh and
the ability to to do something that's
never been done before I mean there's
nothing more exciting than knowing that
when you do something no one has been
there before
you feel like a Pioneer and uh and and
when you when you begin for me
science was always a very difficult
field and for the first time as an adult
I was able to apply scientific
principles for something that created a
visual image
was extraordinary so as I got more and
more excited about the science at the
same time more and more excited about
the image and the two sort of evolves at
the same time and I found that I could
express what I was learning in in an
artistic statement that had emotion
behind it that had
the the desire to to communicate the
excitement that I was having over
discovering about science and light
because so much about what we know in
our mind comes through our eyes
to break that down into to begin to
understand how life behave and then to
be able to turn it around and express it
in some kind of a philosophical and or
emotional statement was there was a
remarkable combination of elements that
managed to pry me away from my
theatrical instincts you actually began
in another aspect of the Arts I guess in
drama we talked earlier with Mary who's
a painter as well as working in
holography do you work in other media as
well or it's
strictly to holography a lot of my work
actually I I always had a side career of
doing small sculpture work
and it just interfaced very well
right with your photography where I was
able to use some of the work that I had
originally done prior to even knowing
the modelography and incorporate that
there was also a link in there because I
went from basically from doing theater
to
um video to film where I where I
performed but then back to video again
with my partner Sam Ray with the New
York holographic labs
um we we did a number of projects
involved with video where we used a lot
of our small sculptures to create
abstract scenarios if you will and uh it
turned out
the models lent themselves very well to
the holographic frame and uh and so
there was a logical step from one thing
to another and then then that became
another thing where the original
sculptures I made Holograms of and then
eventually the whole the sculptures
became exterior to the Hologram and
interrelate with the projected light
images from the Hologram so that became
sort of a little theater for me so now I
was in control of everything
so you're a control freak is that
[Laughter]
thank you I think I'll write that down
put that on my resume
job title out of control freak which has
a couple of meetings depending on where
you put the emphasis in that
that's right now we were talking earlier
before we began the recording about some
courses at the school for the visual
arts can you tell us a little bit about
those courses and what kinds of things
you you know cover in those courses what
experiences students have during the
course it's really a practical course
um
it is as it stands right now at the
schools and elective it's not within the
art department but
um
takes a very curious person to make a
selection like that from the school and
it really it's it's a matter of just
bringing them some very basic steps of
single beam Reflections Transmissions
um our first semester up through image
plane reflection type Holograms and then
the advanced class deals in white liver
white light transmission pornography and
that's where we are right now with the
class and so we're doing one step
rainbows and um it's so fortunate that
we have the center here because we now
have the pulse laser available here so a
lot of the tedious problems that we
often have with making Master Holograms
can be alleviated by at least having a
day out here where we can make Masters
out here we combine those masters with
the Masters that we do on the uh on the
isolation table at New York holographic
labs and we can come up with some pretty
good results but it's a matter of
experimenting and letting them get
curious
and challenging them to use their
creative instincts to try and capitalize
on the medium it's always a difficulty
because it's new I don't really know
what is coming next until we do the shot
but once they see our first test results
and they can begin to to design the
works and generally out of a class we do
come up with some pretty good results
you know
find that the students struggle more
with the I shouldn't put it that way
that sounds so negative but what's more
of a challenge the creative aspect of it
or the technical aspect when you look at
painting or something like that you may
have a you may feel you have more
control if you will but you know the
technical aspect is is can be seemed
difficult I think to people because
they're not as familiar with it maybe
is it not a challenge it's a twofold uh
it's it's clearly a twofold challenge as
it is with any artist coming into the
medium you you have a vision you have an
idea of what you think you'd like to do
but until you really begin to work with
the medium you you're not really on firm
ground yet so when you see what's
possible and what isn't your vision will
change you you ultimately you end up
having to match your idea to what is
possible in technology and clearly
holography is not like a computer world
it's not very instant you you really do
have to stay with
and master it it's like a it's a bit of
a stubborn beast sometimes
I I I'm thinking of marketing Spurs
ride the wild hologram isn't it to take
these birds with you
but but eventually you do come to terms
with it and sometimes some real genuine
magic can happen
find that certain types of students seem
to be attracted to the class as opposed
to you know since it is an elective I
know you mentioned earlier that you have
to be a particularly curious kind of
person probably but are there other
things that you've noticed in in the
students well um
most of the students are photography
Majors a lot of them are photography
major so they have
they have imagery in mind and they have
content in mind
um this is the age where people are
pursuing things that they know are going
to pay off economically
and so it we're not in demand quite yet
because what we do
um is not out there quite so much so
right what I stress what I stress with
the with the students is that if you
never make another hologram in your life
after
doesn't matter we're not we're not
teaching you to be a holographer what
we're trying to do is teach you a little
bit about
the process the concept the recording
process which is so remarkable the
holographic Paradigm is very much a part
of my rap in terms of teaching because I
believe that the way light behaves is a
metaphor for the way life behaves in a
lot of ways and and I think that you can
learn lessons from from holography that
you might not learn
using other media that might have
nothing to do necessarily with your
career but something to do with the way
of thinking or a way of defining your
own universe and uh and so I don't feel
necessarily rejected if my students
don't go on to become famous
holographers although many have and I'm
proud of that not that I made them
good I just introduce them as Rank and
well testify to you can start people but
you don't you don't you don't for them
you have to bring the stuff with you
but I think that there's a lot to be
gained from photography even if you
don't really go into it as a career
clearly it would be great to be able to
go into it as a career but even if not I
think there's so much to be learned as a
part of the process if nothing else
discipline
you can't give up did you think you need
to come into it with discipline or you
learn that discipline and patience it
teaches you discipline for those people
who grow up with a computer where it all
happens right away and actually it
doesn't really do that does it you know
you struggle with everything we work
with if you want to be good at something
you have to really apply yourself and
you have to be dedicated whether it's a
seemingly Simple Technology like
computers or or holography which
seemingly is high-tech and as it turns
out turns out to be more like Trump
light Plumbing
not supposed to say that we're all
plumbers
I've been plummeting ever since no
that's different yeah I should say
plumbing and plummeting
very different concepts
yeah
um well I really appreciate you talking
with the Stan I don't know Frank do you
have any other questions I just wanted
to say that was a great interview and I
want the Holocaust listeners to write in
and let me know do you want me to stay
with the show and I want Michelle Lowe
to take over
no I don't have any more questions
I rest my case
sorry
thanks Dan bye
[Music]